<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-06-05T10:03:22+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">blank</title><subtitle>Personal academic site of Jianghao Liu. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Probing the unimaginable: new data help to understand the nature of aphantasia | Paris Brain Institute</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2023/probing-the-unimaginable-new-data-help-to-understand-the-nature-of-aphantasia-paris-brain-institute/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Probing the unimaginable: new data help to understand the nature of aphantasia | Paris Brain Institute"/><published>2023-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2023-09-08T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2023/probing-the-unimaginable-new-data-help-to-understand-the-nature-of-aphantasia--paris-brain-institute</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2023/probing-the-unimaginable-new-data-help-to-understand-the-nature-of-aphantasia-paris-brain-institute/"><![CDATA[<div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code>		Or
			34,00€
		After 66% tax deduction
	“Think of a white sandy beach on a paradise island. Can you see it?” The ability to visualize a place, object, or place on request varies significantly between individuals. But some people cannot conjure up mental images at all: this trait is known as aphantasia, literally “a defect of imagination.” Aphantasia is not a disorder of the mind but an astonishing cognitive peculiarity that could help us understand how visual mental imagery works. At Paris Brain Institute, Jianghao Liu and Paolo Bartolomeo (Inserm) have shown that people with aphantasia have characteristics that can be described objectively: they are slower than average at processing visual information and have difficulty absorbing it. These observations are described in a recent study published in the journal Cortex.The ability to visualize faces, objects, landscapes, or even scenes from the past exists on a spectrum. While some can picture the layout of a city in minute detail and mentally walk through it, street by street, others have a perfectly blank internal cinema. In this case, we speak of aphantasia—the inability to voluntarily produce the visual mental image corresponding to an idea.People whose aphantasia is congenital—i.e., not due to a stroke, brain injury, or psychiatric illness—become aware of their peculiarity reasonably late in life. Indeed, this small deficit in visualization does not cause any handicap, and they have no reason to suspect they are atypical. Nor do they realize that at the other end of the spectrum are hyperphantasic individuals who can produce mental images as precise as illustrations in a book.“Talking to these people is fascinating. We tend to think that access to visual perception, conceptualization, and memory is the same for everyone. Nothing could be further from the truth,” Paolo Bartolomeo, neurologist and researcher at Paris Brain Institute, says. “Aphantasics cannot mentally picture what their parents, friends, or partner look like when they are away. But they can still describe the physical characteristics of their loved ones: this visual information has been stored, in one way or another”. There is currently a lively debate about the origin of aphantasia. Is it linked to a perceptual deficit? Emotional and psychological factors? A slight difficulty in accessing one’s sensations? To answer this question, Paolo Bartolomeo and Jianghao Liu, a doctoral student in the “Neurophysiology and Functional Neuroimaging” team at Paris Brain Institute, recruited 117 volunteers—including 44 aphantasics, 31 hyperphantasics and 42 people with typical mental imagery—and gave them a mental imagery and visual perception test.“Our test, called the Imagination Perception Battery (BIP), is designed to assess the link between perception and mental imagery through the different visual qualities that enable a scene to be described—such as shape, color, position in space, presence of words or faces“.Participants were asked to look at a blank screen. At the same time, an off-screen voice announced a visual quality (such as ‘shape’), followed by two words corresponding to concepts they had to materialize in their minds as accurately as possible (‘beaver’ and ‘fox’ for example). The voice also gave them a qualifier (such as ‘long’); then, the participants were asked to decide which of the beaver or fox best matched the epithet ‘long’.The speed and relevance of responses were recorded, and the respondents were asked to assess the quality of the mental image they had—or had not—managed to produce from the description. Finally, they had to take a perception test in which the stimuli were presented in a visual format: the long fox appeared in the form of an image accompanied by its audio description without the participants having to picture it. “Our results indicate that the performance of people with aphantasia is equivalent to other groups in terms of perception and the ability to associate a concept with its representation,” Liu comments. “With one exception! Aphantasics are, on average, slower than hyperphantasics and typical imagers when it comes to processing visual information, particularly shapes and colors. They also have little confidence in the accuracy of their answers”.Previous studies have shown that aphantasics are just as quick as other people to answer questions that require manipulating abstract concepts. Therefore, only the processing of visual information is delayed for them. How can this phenomenon be explained?“Participants in the aphantasic group perceive elements of reality accurately and show no deficits in memory and language processing. We believe that they present a slight defect of what we call phenomenal consciousness. This means that they have access to information about shapes, colors, and spatial relationships—but that this visual information does not translate into a visual mental image in conscious experience.This peculiarity is probably compensated by other cognitive strategies, such as mental lists of visual characteristics, which allow aphantasics to remember everything they have seen.”The future of perceptionThese preliminary results are limited by the data collection method, which consisted of an online questionnaire. However, they put us on a promising track to understand how visual mental imagery works. Future studies could reveal the neural mechanisms underlying these observations and, ultimately, help us to understand the visualization deficits specific to stroke patients. “We also hope to develop interventional tools for certain psychiatric illnesses, such as post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD), which is characterized by the eruption of images from traumatic memories. If we could rid patients of these intrusive mental images, it would greatly promote their recovery”, Liu concludes.FINANCEMENT: This study was carried out with the support of Dassault Systèmes, the ANR, and the Foundation for Stroke Research.Liu, Ji., Bartolomeo, P. Probing the unimaginable: The impact of aphantasia on distinct domains of visual mental imagery and visual perception. Cortex, July 5th, 2023. DOI : 10.1016/j.cortex.2023.06.003.Our news on the subject
		Institut du Cerveau
		Hôpital Pitié-Salpêtrière
		47 bd de l'Hôpital, 75013 Paris
	Receive the latest scientific advances, exciting discoveries and exclusive news from Paris Brain Institute.
</code></pre></div></div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[“Think of a white sandy beach on a paradise island. Can you see it?” The ability to visualize a place, object, or place on request varies]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The connectional anatomy of visual mental imagery</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/anatomy-fin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The connectional anatomy of visual mental imagery"/><published>2022-05-02T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2022-05-02T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/anatomy-fin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/anatomy-fin/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-structural-connection-in-the-brain-to-support-the-visual-mental-imagery">What structural connection in the brain to support the visual mental imagery?</h2> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Most of us can use our “mind’s eye” to mentally visualize things that are not in our direct line of sight, an ability known as visual mental imagery. Extensive left temporal damage can impair patients’ visual mental imagery experience, but the critical locus of lesion is unknown. Our recent meta-analysis of 27 fMRI studies of visual mental imagery highlighted a well-delimited region in the left lateral midfusiform gyrus, which was consistently activated during visual mental imagery, and which we called the Fusiform Imagery Node (FIN). Here we describe the connectional anatomy of FIN in neurotypical participants and in RDS, a right-handed patient with an extensive occipitotemporal stroke in the left hemisphere. The stroke provoked right homonymous hemianopia, alexia without agraphia, and color anomia. Despite these deficits, RDS had normal subjective experience of visual mental imagery and reasonably preserved behavioral performance on tests of visual mental imagery of object shape, object color, letters, faces, and spatial relationships. We found that the FIN was spared by the lesion. We then assessed the connectional anatomy of the FIN in the MNI space and in the patient’s native space, by visualizing the fibers of the inferior longitudinal fasciculus (ILF) and of the arcuate fasciculus (AF) passing through the FIN. In both spaces, the ILF connected the FIN with the anterior temporal lobe, and the AF linked it with frontal regions. Our evidence is consistent with the hypothesis that the FIN is a node of a brain network dedicated to voluntary visual mental imagery. The FIN could act as a bridge between visual information and semantic knowledge processed in the anterior temporal lobe and in the language circuits.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/paperfig/anatoconnection.png" alt="anatomical connection"/></p> <p>Link to paper <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007/s00429-022-02505-x">here</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="tractography"/><category term="imagery"/><category term="patients"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the anatomical connection of the FIN]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">the interplay of attention and conscious perception</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/attention-consciousness/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="the interplay of attention and conscious perception"/><published>2022-04-26T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2022-04-26T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/attention-consciousness</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/attention-consciousness/"><![CDATA[<p>How could we be conscious about the external world? Is there a role for attention to help?</p> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Competing theories of consciousness disagree on the role of frontoparietal networks. Here we recorded neural activity from 727 intracerebral contacts in 13 epileptic patients, while they detected near-threshold targets preceded by supra-threshold exogenous cues. Trajectory k-means clustering revealed three patterns: (1) Validly cued seen targets elicit sustained activity in right-hemisphere fronto-temporal regions, connected by superior longitudinal fasciculus (SLF) II/III, and late accumulation activity in bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex and in right-hemisphere orbitofrontal cortex (SLF I/III). (2) Invalidly cued seen targets elicit early, sustained activity in the right-hemisphere reorienting network (SLF III). (3) Seen targets elicit late sustained left dorsolateral prefrontal activity. Task modeling with recurrent neural networks supported the causal contribution of these networks to conscious perception, and elucidated their interplay through excitatory-inhibitory mechanisms. We provide new, compelling evidence on the role of hemisphere-asymmetric frontoparietal networks associated with attentional enhancement and reorienting in conscious perception.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/paperfig/Poster_v4_A0-min.jpg" alt="Poster"/></p> <p>Link to our article<a href="https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2022.04.10.487690v1">here</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="tractography"/><category term="intracranial"/><category term="attention"/><category term="consciousness"/><category term="patients"/><category term="modeling"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[the anatomical connection of the FIN]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Besoin de volontaires pour une étude sur l’imagination en IRM</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/recruitment/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Besoin de volontaires pour une étude sur l’imagination en IRM"/><published>2022-01-27T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-27T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/recruitment</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/recruitment/"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Merci pour votre intérêt, nous avons publié notre première étude IRMf dans notre projet. On a une liste d’attente pour des future études.</strong></p> <p>Si vous voulez suivre les résultats ou participer aux futurs études, merci de remplir <strong><a href="https://forms.gle/BVVgFiCw7tD2r9E1A">ce formulaire</a></strong></p> <h3 id="différence-individuelle-de-limagerie-mentale-visuel">Différence individuelle de l’imagerie mentale visuel</h3> <p>Fermez les yeux et pensez à la Joconde de Léonard de Vinci. Vous regarde-t-elle ou non? Ses cheveux sont-ils bouclés ou raides? La capacité à visualiser des images mentales dépend de chaque individu: certaines personnes ont des images très vives (hyperphantasia), tandis que d’autres n’ont pas d’images mentales (aphantasia). Nous cherchons des volontaires (<strong>aphantasiques ou normophantasique ou hyperphantasiques</strong>) pour participer à une étude scientifique sur l’imagination humaine. L’activité consisterait à faire une IRM fonctionnelle 7 tesla pendant une heure et demie et à imaginer des animaux, couleurs, visages ou lettres etc.</p> <p><strong>Lieux : Institut du Cerveau (ICM), 75013, Paris</strong></p> <p><img src="/assets/img/paperfig/fmripic.png" alt="fmri_pic"/></p> <p><strong>Comment savoir si je peux participer?</strong></p> <ul> <li>Etre capable d’imaginer très vivement OU manquer d’imagerie mentale</li> <li>Etre francophone</li> <li>Avoir une vision normale ou corrigée à la normale (lentilles acceptées)</li> <li>Ne pas être claustrophobe</li> <li>Ne pas avoir d’implants métalliques sur le corps</li> <li>Ne pas présenter d’antécédent de maladie mentale</li> <li>Ne pas être enceinte</li> </ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="Recruitment"/><category term="fmri"/><category term="imagery"/><category term="aphantasia"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[cherche des volontaires pour nos études sur l'imagination]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">hemispheric asymmetries in visual mental imagery</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/vmi-laterality/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hemispheric asymmetries in visual mental imagery"/><published>2022-01-26T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2022-01-26T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/vmi-laterality</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2022/vmi-laterality/"><![CDATA[<h3 id="how-does-evidence-from-brain-damaged-patients-cortical-stimulation-and-neuroimaging-tell-us-about-the-brain-laterality-of-visual-imagery">How does evidence from brain-damaged patients, cortical stimulation and neuroimaging tell us about the brain laterality of visual imagery?</h3> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>Visual mental imagery is the faculty whereby we can “visualize” objects that are not in our line of sight. Longstanding evidence dating back over thirty years has shown that unilateral brain lesions, especially in the left temporal lobe, can impair aspects of this ability. Yet, there is currently no attempt to identify analogies between these neuropsychological findings of hemispheric asymmetry and those from other neuroscientific approaches. Here, we present a critical review of the available literature on the hemispheric laterality of visual mental imagery, by looking at cross-method patterns of evidence in the domains of lesion neuropsychology, neuroimaging, and direct cortical stimulation. Results can be summarized under three main axes. First, frontoparietal networks in both hemispheres appear to be associated with visual mental imagery. Second, lateralization patterns emerge in the temporal lobes, with the left inferior temporal lobe being the most common finding in the literature for endogenously generated images, especially, but not exclusively, when orthographic material is used to ignite imagery. Third, an opposite pattern of hemispheric laterality emerges when visual mental images are induced by exogenous stimulation; direct cortical electrical stimulation tends to produce visual imagery experiences predominantly when applied to the right temporal lobe. These patterns of hemispheric asymmetry are difficult to reconcile with the dominant model of visual mental imagery, which emphasizes the implication of early sensory cortices. They suggest instead that visual mental imagery relies on large-scale brain networks, with a crucial participation of high-level visual regions in the temporal lobes.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/paperfig/vmi_laterality.JPG" alt="brain laterality"/> <br/></p> <p>Link to paper <a href="https://link.springer.com/article/10.1007%2Fs00429-021-02277-w">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="fmri"/><category term="imagery"/><category term="patients"/><category term="review"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[review of evidence of neuroimaging, neurological patients and electrical stimulation]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">tests de Imagerie-Perception</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2020/eBIP-fr/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="tests de Imagerie-Perception"/><published>2020-10-19T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2020/eBIP-fr</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2020/eBIP-fr/"><![CDATA[<p>Une nouvelle batterie de tests permet grâce à differentes variables (perception, imagerie, vivacité) d’évaluer votre capacité à générer des images mentales.</p> <p><img src="/assets/img/paperfig/bip2protocol.png" alt="bip2protocol"/></p> <p><strong>Attention, ce test fonctionne uniquement sur un ordinateur avec clavier. La version sur portable est en cours de développement.</strong></p> <p>Le saviez-vous? Environ 5% de la population ne peut pas imaginer dans le sens de <em>visualisation</em> ou <em>création d’images mentales</em>. Ces individus ne sont par exemple pas capables d’imaginer le visage de leur propre petit/petite ami/amie ou bien d’imaginer une plage ou une forêt. Nous appelons cela <strong>l’aphantasie</strong>. Ces personnes peuvent rencontrer des difficultés dans l’imagination d’objets, des visages, des couleurs ou des lettres, etc.</p> <p>Lors de notre projet de recherche sur <strong>l’imagerie visuelle mentale</strong> (VMI), nous avons conçu une batterie de tests qui contient plusieurs domaines évalués, y compris un test classique de vivacité de l’image mentale.</p> <p>Le test comprend trois parties, environ 25 minutes en total:</p> <ul> <li>test de vivacité de l’image mentale (3 mins)</li> <li>test de l’imagerie mentale visuelle (15 mins)</li> <li>test de perception visuelle (5 mins)</li> </ul> <p>Après chaque partie, nous vous donnerons vos résultats. Vous pourrez ainsi les comparer avec nos références qui se trouvent en bas de cette page.</p> <p>Vous pouvez faire ces tests en cliquant sur le bouton ici : (L’utilisation de <strong>Google Chrome</strong> ou <strong>Safari</strong> est recommandé parce que <em>Firefox</em> a un bug)</p> <p><button class="btn btn-success btn-large" style="background-color: #7ED321;width: 180px;height: 60px;color: #FFFFFF" onclick=" window.open('https://run.pavlovia.org/liujianghao/ebiponline/html','_blank')">Clique pour te tester!</button></p> <p>N’hésitez pas à diffuser ce test.</p> <p>Si vous avez des commentaires, vous pouvez nous écrire par mail à <u>jianghaolouisliu@gmail.com</u>.</p> <p>Nous avons recruté des volontaires aphantasiques et normaux pour une expérimentation en IRM fonctionnel. Si vous voulez suivre les résultats ou participer aux futurs études, merci de remplir <strong><a href="https://forms.gle/BVVgFiCw7tD2r9E1A">ce formulaire</a></strong>.</p> <p><em>Pour savoir plus sur notre projet en l’imagerie mentale visuel: <a href="/project/">cliquer ici</a></em></p> <p><strong>Référence de résultats (plus de 40 participants):</strong></p> <p><em>Partie 1: test de vivacité de l’image mentale</em><br/> 16 &lt;= score &lt; 46: <strong>Faible</strong><br/> 46 &lt;= score &lt; 65: <strong>Moyen</strong><br/> 65 &lt;= score &lt; 80: <strong>Elevé</strong></p> <p><em>Partie 2: test de l’imagerie mental visuel</em><br/> La fourchette pour la plus part des gens:</p> <ul> <li>Forme: <em>75%-100%</em></li> <li>Couleur: <em>58.33%-100%</em></li> <li>Lettre: <em>83.33%-100%</em></li> <li>Visage: <em>66.66%-100%</em></li> <li>Carte: <em>75%-100%</em></li> </ul> <p><em>Partie 3: test de la perception</em><br/> <em>83.33%-100%</em></p> <p>Les résultats de références sont en cours de renouvèlement en incluant plus de participants.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="tests"/><category term="imagery"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Enhanced Battery of Imagery and Perception]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">a meta-analysis of neuroimaging evidence of visual mental imagery</title><link href="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2020/metaanalysis/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="a meta-analysis of neuroimaging evidence of visual mental imagery"/><published>2020-10-19T16:40:16+00:00</published><updated>2020-10-19T16:40:16+00:00</updated><id>https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2020/metaanalysis</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jianghao-liu.github.io/blog/2020/metaanalysis/"><![CDATA[<h2 id="what-do-we-know-about-the-neural-basis-of-visual-mental-imagery-from-past-fmri-studies">What do we know about the neural basis of visual mental imagery from past fMRI studies?</h2> <h3 id="abstract">Abstract</h3> <p>The dominant neural model of visual mental imagery (VMI) stipulates that memories from the medial temporal lobe acquire sensory features in early visual areas. However, neurological patients with damage restricted to the occipital cortex typically show perfectly vivid VMI, while more anterior damages extending into the temporal lobe, especially in the left hemisphere, often cause VMI impairments. Here we present two major results reconciling neuroimaging findings in neurotypical subjects with the performance of brain-damaged patients: (1) A large-scale meta-analysis of 46 fMRI studies, of which 27 investigated specifically visual mental imagery, revealed that VMI engages fronto-parietal networks and a well-delimited region in the left fusiform gyrus. (2) A Bayesian analysis showed no evidence for imagery-related activity in early visual cortices. We propose a revised neural model of VMI that draws inspiration from recent cytoarchitectonic and lesion studies, whereby fronto-parietal networks initiate, modulate, and maintain activity in a core temporal network centered on the fusiform imagery node, a high-level visual region in the left fusiform gyrus.</p> <p><br/> <img src="/assets/img/paperfig/metaanalysis.jpg" alt="Brain location of the Fusiform Imagery Node" style="max-width: 600px; width: 100%; height: auto; display: block; margin: 0 auto;" zoomable="true"/></p> <figcaption style="font-style: italic; margin-top: 10px; color: #555;"> Figure 1. Brain location of the Fusiform Imagery Node (FIN) identified through meta-analysis. <br/><span style="font-size: 0.9em; color: #777;">(MNI coordinates: x=-42, y=-54, z=-18)</span> </figcaption> <p><br/> </p> <p>Find our paper <a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S0149763420307041">here</a>.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="science"/><category term="fmri"/><category term="imagery"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[meta-analysis of visual mental imagery]]></summary></entry></feed>